Guide to the 1914 Time Capsule Collection 1614-1914 MS 2995
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
1914 Time Capsule Collection
1614 - 1914
MS 2995
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.6 Linear feet
Collection of material from a Time Capsule created in 1914 by the Lower Wall Street Business Men's Association.
Scope and Contents note
The time capsule included books, pamphlets, newspapers, medals, and a copy of a pre-Revolutionary War letter from 1774. A telegram from Governor Martin Glynn to his successor in 1974 was also enclosed, with a message expressing “hope and good will” that the challenges he faced would be solved by then. Other items include a portrait, lithograph, and related loose documents. All items in the time capsule have been very well preserved.
Biographical/Historical note
The term "time capsule" was first used at New York World’s Fair in 1939, but the practice of preserving materials in a sealed box to help future generations understand the past dates back to at least 1876, when a proto-time capsule was introduced at the Philadelphia Exposition. In 1914, another early time capsule was created by a group of merchants called the Lower Wall Street Business Men’s Association. It was launched on May 23, 1914 as a part of the tri-centennial celebrations of the New Netherland Company’s chartering in 1614 and the beginnings of Dutch North American colonialism. The time capsule was placed in a richly ornamented bronze casket which was ceremoniously enclosed by a former mayor and entrusted to the New York Historical Society. The chest was to remain sealed until the year 1974, the bicentennial of New York’s appeal for the colonies to form a union, but it was forgotten in a storage site until the late 1990s. Historians decided to wait until the 100th year anniversary to open it since they had already missed the intended date. Upon its opening on October 8th 2014, it was possibly the oldest unopened time capsule in the world.
To keep the tradition alive, N-YHS created a new time capsule in 2014 with the help of local students, who selected items that reflect life in the early 21st century for the education of New Yorkers a hundred years in the future.
Provenance
Gift of the Lower Wall Street Business Men's Association, 1914.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Inter-library loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Arrangement note
This collection has been arranged into three series by subject: 1. Publications and pamphlets 2. Newspapers 3. Loose documents
- Series I: Publications and pamphlets
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains a variety of bound volumes and publications which have been individually listed.
  - A History of The Bank of New York, by Henry W. Domett, 1784-1884 (Box 1)
  - Arbitration Records of the Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, 1779-1792, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York, 1768-1902 (Box 1)
  - Yearbook of the Holland Society of New York, 1913 (Box 1)
  - The New York Historical Society, 1804-1904 (Box 1)
  - Constitution of the New York Stock Exchange, 1914 (Box 1)
  - Marine Society of New York, 1913 (Box 1)
  - The New York Stock Exchange, by Francis L. Eames, 1894 (Box 1)
  - Yearbook of the Society of Sons of the Revolution in the State of New York, 1899 (Box 1)
  - Eagle Almanac, 1914 (Box 1)
  - Yearbook of the Daughters of the Cincinnati, 1910 - 1911 (Box 1)
  - The New York Society Library, Shareholders and Officers, 1914 (Box 1)
  - New York Produce Exchange Report, July 1, 1912 - July 1, 1913 (Box 1)
  - The World Almanac and Encyclopedia, 1913 (Box 1)
  - American Art in Bronze and Iron, 1910 (Box 1)
  - The New York Stock Exchange Directory, January, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 25th Annual report of board of managers of the Coffee Exchange of the city of New York, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Commercial Tercentenary of New York, 1614-1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Program of ceremonies connected with the unveiling of the tablet at the Merchants Coffee House, May 23, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - History and Reminicences of Lower Wall Street and Vicinity, by Abram Wakeman, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Portraits for incorporation into History and Reminicences of Lower Wall Street and Vicinity, by Abram Wakeman (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Illustrations for incorporation into History and Reminicences of Lower Wall Street and Vicinity, by Abram Wakeman (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bank of Manhattan - History, Origin, Progress (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bank of Manhattan - Historic buildings now standing in New York which were erected prior to 1800 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - New York Society Library - Annual Report, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - New York Society Library - History, Charters, By-Laws, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - New York Society Library - List of shareholders, officers, and benefactors (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 117th annual report of the New York Hospital of the State of New York (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - St John's Lodge No.1 A.Y.M, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - St John's Lodge, By-laws, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - St John's Lodge, Archives, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - St John's Lodge, Sesqui-Centennial Anniversary, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - St John's Lodge, Proceedings of the Centennial Celebration, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - St John's Lodge, Proceedings of the Sesqui-Centennial Celebration, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - New York Public Library, Central Buildings Guide (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Simmons' Spice Mill, May, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Tea and Coffee Trade Journal, May, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Daughters of the Cincinnati, Annual Meeting Report, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Saint Andrews Society of the State of New York, Annual Report, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Saint Andrews Society of the State of New York, roster of membership, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sons of the revolution, Reports and Proceedings, 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Newspapers, May 1914
  - Evening Telegram, May 15, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 1)
  - Evening Mail, May 19, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 1)
  - Deutches Journal, May 17, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 1)
  - The World Paper, May 17 & 18, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 2)
  - New York Tribune, May 17 & 18, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 3)
  - The Globe and Commercial Advertiser, May 2 & 15, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 3)
  - The Standard Union, May 19, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 4)
  - The New York Times, May 23, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 4)
  - New York Herald, May 15, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 4)
- Series III: Loose Documents, 1914
  - Documents relating to the Lower Wall Street Business Men's Association (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes medal for the Vice President of the Association
  - Telegram from Governor Martin Glynn, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lithograph pamphlet of the New York 45th Grand Lodge Association convention (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Portrait of Miss Ellen Jay- Daguerreotype, by Hollinger & Co, 582 5th Avenue, NY, May 23, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 5)
  - Loose envelopes, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 5)
  - Commercially produced copy of pre-Revolutionary War letter from 1774 and accompanying documents, 1774, 1914 (Oversize OS Small, Folder 5)